<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great day of chancery A sermon preached at White-Hall, the last day of October. 1619. By Iames Forsith, one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinarie.</title>
            <author>Forsyth, James, fl. 1615-1619.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01078</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11192</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105640</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841367</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841367</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5944</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01078)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5944)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1023:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great day of chancery A sermon preached at White-Hall, the last day of October. 1619. By Iames Forsith, one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinarie.</title>
                  <author>Forsyth, James, fl. 1615-1619.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.C.XIX. [1619]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5944:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5944:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE FRANCIS Lord VERVLAM, Lord high Chancellor of England, and one of his MAIESTIES moſt Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>priuie Counſell: Grace and peace from God the Father, in the mediation of his Sonne Ieſu Chriſt, and by the operation of the bleſſed Spirit for euer. Amen.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> did preach the word of God at <hi>Antioch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 13.14</note> the people ſeemed to giue ſuch attendance vnto their words of exhortation, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="42"/> that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to heare the ſame the
<pb facs="tcp:5944:2"/>next <hi>Sabboath day.</hi> When I preached this Sermon at Court, the auditors did ſeeme to giue ſuch attention vnto what was ſpoken, (although vnworthy of their meaneſt attention) that they did ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire to ſee in writing what that day they had heard by preaching, <hi>Viſus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim eſt perfectior ſenſus:</hi> ſo that my weake labours, <hi>through Gods bleſsing,</hi> paſſed along the Court, like <hi>plaine honeſtie,</hi> with euery mans good leaue and liking: and if this place had beene the furtheſt period, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had beene eaſed of ſome fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture paines. But then it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:5944:2"/>ſome, <hi>Honorable and worthy friends,</hi> to impoſe vpon mee this ſecond view: and ſurely <hi>pruritus ſcribendi,</hi> the diſeaſe of our age, had almoſt hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered me; for I know <hi>litera ſcripta manet,</hi> and is more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to cenſure, then <hi>quod au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus auditur:</hi> for which cauſe I did not at the firſt yeelde. Yet at laſt, vpon more ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deliberation, (leaſt I ſhould haue encurred the breach of loue of ſome <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and much respected friends:</hi> as alſo the cenſorious conceit of ſome <hi>ſupercilious Stoickes:</hi>) I reſolued <hi>prodere in vulgus,</hi> to lye <hi>Noah-like,</hi> in the Tent
<pb facs="tcp:5944:3"/>doore, that euery ſcoffing <hi>Cham</hi> may ſmile at my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe: And becauſe that a ſeruant of meane birth and qualitie is many times pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred aboue his worth, for <hi>his Lord and Maſters ſake;</hi> I haue therefore made choiſe of your <hi>Honorable Patronage,</hi> being at that time when it was deliuered, one of my moſt Noble Auditors. <hi>Vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam eſſet poſsibile me vnum eſſe ex principibus offerre geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas ad ornamentum Pontificis; ſed quia haec ſupra me ſunt, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te vel pilos caprarum habere merear in Tabernaculo Dei,</hi> as <hi>Origen</hi> elegantly; I wiſh that
<pb facs="tcp:5944:3"/>I could ſpeak any thing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of this Text, or your <hi>Honours Dedication.</hi> A <hi>day</hi> it is, and that a great one, when not onely all criminall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes will be heard, as in the Court of the Kings Bench; as alſo euery mans caſe ſhall be adiudged, as at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-pleas barre: but when, and where the iuſt Iudge of all the world, will accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the euidence of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans conſcience, diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute righteous Iudgement; and therefore more properly I call it <hi>The great day of Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery:</hi> plaine it is, that the <hi>ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest</hi> and moſt <hi>Ignorant,</hi> may
<pb facs="tcp:5944:4"/>vnderſtand it: yet (as I thinke) profitable, that the moſt <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>learned</hi> may reape ſome inſtruction by it: the beſt Remembrancer that Iudges can haue about them, is to remember the <hi>day of Iudgement; Summus enim iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex iudicata reiudicabit:</hi> and vnto whom much is giuen, of him much ſhall bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in that day: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeech the Lord of heauen and earth, to aſſiſt your <hi>Honour</hi> with his grace and holy Spirit, that you may Honourably long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, as hitherto a good Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticiar, in that place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
<pb facs="tcp:5944:4"/>you are worthily called, to his glory, and your eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall comfort, that you may ſtand boldly before the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall in that day. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in all ſeruice, in the Lord, <hi>IAMES FORSITH.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5944:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5944:5"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Xpect not</hi> (cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle READER,) <hi>Critical conceits,</hi> nec ipſum Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceronem, <hi>not any Rhetoricall fine phraſes, in this plaine Sermon: for we ought to come to the people, as Saint Paul ſpeaketh;</hi> not with the wiſedome of words,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.4.</note> but plaine euidence of the Spirit; <hi>to benefit and not to fit the humour, is my deſire: not to pleaſe, but to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe rather doe I ſeeke: that their</hi> ſorrow might bee godly <hi>againſt ſinne to cauſe repentance</hi> not to bee repented of. <hi>The dangerous ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and damnable Impietie of theſe laſt and perillous times, which euery</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:5944:6"/>true iudicious eye diſcerneth, and euery good Chriſtian lamenteth, did cauſe mee to chooſe this Text; that hereby I might rouze vp all <hi>careleſſe ſleepers</hi> and <hi>ſluggiſh ſlumberers</hi> from their ſecured ſafety. for ſome there be <hi>(I pray God not too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny)</hi> that hardly entertaine at any time, ſo much as any ſhew of <hi>deſire</hi> or <hi>care</hi> how they ſhall appeare <hi>in that day;</hi> as if they had made a <hi>coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with death and hell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 28.15.</note> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>(I thinke)</hi> they beleeue that falſe Axiome of Atheiſme, that there is neither <hi>heauen nor hell;</hi> nor yet ſuch a day as is ſpoken of here: for their actions ſeeme ſuch, as theſe in <hi>Iob</hi> bidding the Almightie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from them,
<note place="margin">Iob. 21.14.</note> 
               <hi>for they deſire not the knowledge of his waies,</hi> and ſtand ſcoffing like theſe Mockers in <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pet. 3.4.</note> that aske, Where is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of his comming? Such monſters there bee vnder the habite of men,
<pb facs="tcp:5944:6"/>worſe then the very deuils them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues:
<note place="margin">Ia. 2.19.</note> for the <hi>deuils beleeue this day, and tremble</hi> in remembrance of it: for whoſe proſperitie (I thinke charitably of all:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.8.</note> 
               <hi>de viuo ſperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum)</hi> as <hi>for my brethren and companions ſake,</hi> I am bound to pray, and he that is the ſearcher of the heart knoweth,
<note place="margin">Ro. 10.1.</note> 
               <hi>that mine heart deſireth their conuerſion,</hi> that all men and women that haue heard of the trueth, may truly receiue this true doctrine concerning Chriſt, and his comming to Iudgement: that we all being in our liues reformed, in our conſciences cleared, by true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of our ſinnes, and that euery day wee may be readie,
<note place="margin">Luc. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>as a people prepared for the Lord;</hi> and my prayer dayly ſhall be vnto Almightie God, with the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>for my ſelfe and all Chriſtians,</hi> that he may grant vs, <hi>according to the riches of his glorie, that wee may
<pb facs="tcp:5944:7"/>be ſtrengthened in the Inner man, that Chriſt may dwell in our hearts by faith in this life.</hi> ſo that in that day wee may bee freed from Iudgement, and after that day conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually dwell with Christ in glory. <hi>Vnto that God, that brought Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt againe from the dead, and made him Iudge of quicke and dead:
<note place="margin">Eph. 3.20.</note> that is able to doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding abundantly aboue all that wee aske or thinke, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the power that worketh in vs, be praiſe in the Church by Chriſt Ieſus throughout all gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord IAMES FORSITH.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>S. Michaels in the Quern, London,</hi> 
                  <date>20. Nouemb. <hi>1619.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5944:7"/>
            <head>THE GREAT DAY of Chancery.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. COR. 5.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>We muſt all appeare (or be manifeſted) before the Tribunall ſeat of Christ.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Text (as I thinke) fit to be preached at all times, and to all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: <hi>Recordare nouiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima, &amp; non peccabis in aeternu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſaith the Son of <hi>Syrach,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclus. 7.36.</note> Let any man or woman of what degree ſoeuer, alwaies remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their <hi>laſt end,</hi> and it will bridle them in their courſes, and curbe them in their waies: the remembrance of death is the way to life; and for a man diſcreetly to conſider the <hi>day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> will cauſe him <hi>Iudiciouſly</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his accompts againſt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5944:8"/>comming:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amb. ad Virgin. lapſ. Cap.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>Si mente cornerent pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catores quale Iudicium imminet mundo,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> if ſinners did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what great Iudgement is to come vpon the world, they would not hunt ſo much after worldly vanities, and plunge themſelues ſo deep into earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dirt as they do.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hierom. in Reg. Mona. Cap.</hi> 30.</note> Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> ſaith of himſelfe, that he was very carefull ouer his waies, and fearefull in his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; for (ſaith he) whether I eate or drinke, or whatſoeuer I doe I conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually thinke, that I heare this ſound in mine eare; <hi>Riſe vp, ye dead, and come vnto Iudgement.</hi> It was <hi>Origens</hi> conceit, that the Prieſt had bells in the lower parts of his garment, to put the people in mind of <hi>Iudgment:</hi> The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of which many times is a terror to the godly;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.120.</note> 
               <hi>My fleſh trembleth for feare of thee, and I am afraid of thy Iudgements,</hi> ſaith the ſweete ſinger of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and the wicked often are curbed by it, <hi>Oderuut peccare mali formidine poenae.</hi> The Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt tels vs that this is a cauſe, why the wicked man doth ſo much delight in ſinne, and make ſuch a progreſſe in Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5944:8"/>becauſe <hi>Gods Iudgements are farre out of his ſight;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 10.5.</note> the remembrance of the <hi>Tribunall,</hi> the feare of <hi>execution,</hi> the conſideration of the <hi>dungeon,</hi> the darkneſſe and blackneſſe of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe <hi>pit,</hi> the <hi>weeping, wailing,</hi> and <hi>gnaſhing of teeth,</hi> are able to reclaime the moſt wicked, and make them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine their euill waies, knowing that they muſt come to <hi>Iudgement.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering then the terror of the day, <hi>we perſwade men,</hi> as it is in the next verſe, <hi>That we may couet, that both dwelling at home, and remouing from home, we may be acceptable to him,</hi> as it is in the verſe precedent.</p>
            <p>Thus I haue made way to the <hi>Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi> where I intend to take vp my ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that I may take a full view of the great <hi>Aſſembly</hi> cited before the ſeate of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and there orderly obſerue this generall appearance: and firſt obſerue the <hi>perſons cited</hi> to appeare, and you ſhall finde them <hi>all we.</hi> 2. marke the <hi>manner</hi> of their appearance, which is well ſet forth in the word <hi>manifeſted.</hi> 3. the <hi>neceſſitie</hi> of appearance in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5944:9"/>word <hi>oportet, muſt.</hi> 4. the place where it ſhall be, and it is ſaid, before the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall.</hi> 5. the <hi>Iudge,</hi> what he is, or who hee is before whom, and he is <hi>Christ.</hi> In the firſt you may ſee a <hi>generalitie,</hi> for number; in the ſecond a plaine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, or <hi>Charitie</hi> of euidence in the manner; in the third, an <hi>ineuitabilitie,</hi> and no reſiſtance of the matter; in the fourth, the <hi>glory</hi> or <hi>maieſtie</hi> of the place, being a <hi>Tribunall:</hi> and laſtly, in the Iudge, <hi>equity</hi> and <hi>humanitie,</hi> for he is <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt place,
<note place="margin">The perſons ſummoned. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the perſons are ſet downe in generall to be <hi>all we,</hi> without exception, <hi>Clergie, Laitie, King, Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>People;</hi> it will not bee ſuch an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly as that of king <hi>Ahaſhueroſh,</hi> of his Nobles, Princes, and Captaines onely:
<note place="margin">Eſter. 1.3.</note> nor ſuch as the biddings of rich men to their feaſts, of their rich <hi>neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 14.12.</note> 
               <hi>kinsfolke,</hi> and <hi>acquaintance:</hi> but like the inuitation of that houſholder in the Goſpel, that ſent his ſeruants at ſupper time, to compell all to come in.
<note place="margin">Ibidem. 23.</note> In like manner ſhall it bee in that great day, that all of what degree ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5944:9"/>ſort, or ſexe, high, or low, rich or poore, old or young: that haue beene, that are, that ſhall be, muſt generally appeare: <hi>The howre ſhall come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.28.29.</note> (ſaith our bleſſed Sauiour) <hi>in the which all that are in the graues ſhall heare his voyce, and they ſhall come forth that haue done good vnto the reſurrection of life, and they that haue done euill, vnto the reſurrection of condemnation. Behold he commeth with clouds, and euery eye ſhall ſee him, yea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen they which pierced him, and all the kinreds of the earth ſhall waile before him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plinie</hi> reporteth of the <hi>Lyoneſſe,</hi> that ſhe brings forth her whelps dead, and ſo remaine for the ſpace of three dayes, vntill the <hi>Lyon</hi> (comming neere to the place where they lye) lift vp his voyce, and roare ſo fiercely, that preſently they are raiſed from death to life: The Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> tels vs the like of the <hi>Lyon</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 25.30.31.</note> 
               <hi>That hee ſhall roare from aboue, and thruſt out his voyce from his holy habitation, he ſhall cry aloud as they that preſſe the Grapes, his ſound ſhall come to the ends of the earth, and he will enter into Iudgement with all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5944:10"/>fleſh:</hi> ſo that with his voyce all that are dead ſhall bee raiſed to life, and ſhall come and ſtand before him. In that day none ſhall anſwer by a <hi>proxie,</hi> no neighbour or friend anſwer for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, no excuſe nor pretence ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile;
<note place="margin">Apoc. 6.15.16</note> 
               <hi>The Kings of the earth, the great men, the rich men, the chiefe Captaines, and the mightie men, euery bondman, and euery free man hid themſelues in dens, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the rockes of the mountaines, and ſaid vnto the hills, fall on vs, and to the rockes, couer vs from the preſence of the Lambe that ſitteth on the Throne.</hi> Theſe, you ſee, would be couered, but cannot, they would haue others to ſtand for them, but it will not be; their authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (although great in the world while they liued) will not ſerue, riches will not help, nor honour auaile; neither bribes nor friends can ſaue them from their appearance before that irefull Iudge; that <hi>Iudge</hi> will admit no man to make way for malefactors, that they ſhould not bee brought forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Iudgement,</hi> neither ſhall their bee any ſtanding by, that dare for <hi>Money</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:5944:10"/>excuſe any mans appearance, or free him from the ſeate of Iuſtice. I reade (ſaith <hi>Chryſostome</hi>) that the man that had not on a <hi>wedding garment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom.</hi> 22. <hi>ad popul. Antioch.</hi>
               </note> was thruſt out from the feaſt: but I read not (ſaith hee) that any made requeſt for him: I heare that hee that hid his <hi>talent</hi> in the earth, was bound hand and foot, and caſt into vtter darkneſſe, and none to ſpeake for him: I ſee the fiue fooliſh virgins ſhut out of the <hi>wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding chamber,</hi> and none to make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for them. <hi>Huius diei terror crit inexplicabilis, &amp; veniet Iudex inexora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis:</hi> The terror and dread of this day is vnexplicable, and the Iudge will come inexorable. The <hi>Angels</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues will come out in feare: and if in that day the Iuſt ſhall hardly be ſaued, <hi>Where or how ſhall the ſinner and vngodly appeare. &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I paſſe further, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> I muſt anſwere an obiection that commeth in my way; the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſaith, <hi>That hee that beleeueth hath euerlaſting life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.24.</note> 
               <hi>and ſhall not come to Iudgement, but ſhall paſſe from death vnto life:</hi> and that the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5944:11"/>wicked ſhall not riſe vppe,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.6.</note> nor ſtand in Iudgement,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hilar. in Pſa.</hi> 1. <hi>Orig. in Iob l.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 272.</note> for he that beleeueth not, is <hi>iudged already.</hi> Some of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents did thinke, by theſe places, that neither the godly faithfull, nor wicked infidell, ſhould come to Iudgement, but they that are, <hi>inter Impios pioſque medij,</hi> of the middle ſort which are in the faith, &amp; yet liue not thereafter: this opinion is plainely confuted in my text,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambr. ſerm.</hi> 20. <hi>in Pſalm.</hi> 119.</note> 
               <hi>nam oportet nos omnes, for we must all appeare.</hi> S. <hi>Ambr.</hi> thought that the godly onely ſhould come to Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>quia festinant innoxij ad Iudicium,</hi> for they that are innocent make haſt to Iudgement, becauſe they doe not feare it, but the vngodly doe ſo trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at it, that they dare not come neere it: but our bleſſed Apoſtle, ſaith plainely,
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.3.</note> that the wicked man aboue all other ſhall not eſcape the iudgement of God. But Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wel expound theſe places thus, The godly ſhall not come <hi>in iudicium con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnationis,</hi> vnto Iudgement of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, as it is in the Goſpel, nor the wicked ſhall not come <hi>in Iudicium
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5944:11"/>Electionis,</hi> vnto iudgement of Election with the godly. Saint <hi>Chryſostome</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that place, <hi>that the wicked are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged already,</hi> doth ſay thus; He that hath committed murther, although hee bee not by the Iudge condemned, <hi>actu prolationis,</hi> by ſentence giuen, yet by the Law he is condemned: for the Law ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi> Hee that beleeueth not, hath the cauſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation in himſelfe, although the ſentence bee not pronounced againſt him vntill the day of <hi>Iudgement.</hi> The Lord ſaid vnto <hi>Adam, In what day ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer thou eateſt of the fruit thou ſhalt de the death.</hi> The Lord ſpake not this, meaning preſently to deſtroy <hi>Adam,</hi> but to ſhew that <hi>Adam</hi> immediately vpon taſting thereof, had the cauſe of death in himſelfe. But to conclude this point, neither godly, nor godleſſe, although the one cleared in his owne conſcience, the other condemned, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the cauſe of condemnation in himſelfe, ſhall eſcape this Iudgement ſeat. For we muſt all appeare, &amp;c. </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> Another obiection may bee made
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5944:12"/>vpon this text, concerning <hi>little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> whether they that haue miſcaried before the birth, or after birth, that haue died without <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> or after <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> that haue departed before they come to knowledge, ſhall come to Iudgement. It is but a Popiſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit to imagine that ſuch ſhall ſtand on the Iudges left hand in that day.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thom. Aquinas</hi> 4. <hi>diſt.</hi> 7. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>art.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Aquinas</hi> thinkes that little children ſhall appeare in that day not to bee iudged, but to ſee the glory of the Iudge: but my text is plaine, that all, both old and young, great and ſmall, ſhall appeare. And ſurely in that day, all ſhall goe either vnder the ſentence of <hi>Goe yee curſed,</hi> or <hi>Come yee bleſſed.</hi> Let this doctrine conuince the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vie.</note> that expect not ſuch a time: and likewiſe let it condemne the <hi>Wicked,</hi> that put off this day from them, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as they ſhew in their actions) that they ſhall not come to Iudgement. Let vs that profeſſe Chriſt ſtand in awe of his comming, and expect this day; <hi>knowing the terror of the day, wee perſwade men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. in Pſa.</hi> 93.</note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Augustine</hi> compares
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5944:12"/>all Chriſtians vnto ſchollars, that come to render an accompt vnto their maſters, of that which they haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, they doe it not without feare; ſo ſhould wee tremble to remember this day,
<note place="margin">Sine metu Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garum.</note> when we ſhall giue account of all things giuen to vs in charge. Know this, that the <hi>Gyants</hi> before the floode could not deliuer themſelues from the deluge by their ſtrength; that <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> for all his power and forces, could not ſaue himſelfe from the ouerthrow in the redde Sea; that the <hi>rich glutton</hi> in the Goſpel, could not with all his wealth, free himſelfe from hell tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Neither ſhall Kings nor Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates; Iudges, nor Magiſtrates; poore, nor rich, deliuer themſelues from this Iudgement: ſome ſhall iudge, others bee iudged, <hi>but all muſt appeare.</hi> God grant wee may be found worthy of the Iudges comming. Amen. </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the ſecond place wee are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the <hi>euidence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The maner how wee ſhal appeare. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> or the manner of our appearing, or rather the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe that appeare in that great
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5944:13"/>day. Our bleſſed <hi>Apostle</hi> repeating the ſame words in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi> doth vſe another word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſtabimus, wee ſhall ſtand,</hi> and Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſeemes to fauour that word better, becauſe (ſaith hee) the Pſalmiſt ſayth,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>the wicked ſhall not ſtand in Iudgement.</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> encli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth rather to ſtand in this ſenſe, but <hi>Theoph. Theodor.</hi> and all the moderne doe reade it rather <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to bee manifeſted,</hi> and not to ſtand: and I thinke the word is more <hi>Emphaticall</hi> and doth expreſſe better the manner of our appearing in that day: for many ſtand before a Iudge, that are not manifeſted, or well knowne vnto the Iudge.
<note place="margin">Gen. 39.18.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Putiphars</hi> wife ſtood before <hi>Putiphar;</hi> ſhee accuſed <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and hee did caſt him into priſon; but <hi>Putiphar</hi> knew neither the hypocriſie of the one, nor the integritie of the other. But it ſhall not be ſo with this Iudge concerning thoſe that ſtand before him: hee is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſearcher of the heart; Thou haſtryed me, and knowen me,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5944:13"/>ſayth the Prophet <hi>Dauid:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 139.1.</note> thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt my thoughts long before, there is not a word in my tongue but thou knoweſt it altogether. <hi>Quid in Babilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne tutum ſi Ieruſalem manet ſcrut mium,</hi> ſayth holy <hi>Bernard.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern. Ser.</hi> 55. <hi>in Cant.</hi>
               </note> If hee doth ſo narrowly marke the actions of the godly, for which they ſhall not come to <hi>iudgement,</hi> how much more doth hee obſerue the <hi>abhominations</hi> of the wicked,
<note place="margin">Hebr. 4.13.</note> for which they ſhall bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in iudgement; <hi>Omnia illi nuda &amp; manifeſta erunt,</hi> all things ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare plainely vnto him, when wee ſhall ſtand naked before him, not vnto him alone, but vnto the whole world:
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>cuncta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cunctorum cunctis arcana pate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt. Iudge nothing before the time, vntill the Lord come, who will ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten things that bee hid in darkeneſſe, and make the counſels of the heart ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest,</hi> ſayth the Apoſtle. <hi>Ecce homo &amp; opera eius,</hi> will the Lord ſay, (ſayth S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ierome</hi> vpon that text) Behold the man and his workes, when hee doth giue vnto euery man according to his workes, there is nothing now hid,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5944:14"/>which, then, ſhall not bee manifeſted. Whatſoeuer hath bin done in darknes ſhall then bee brought vnto the light: <hi>and whatſoeuer men haue ſpoken in the eare, ſhall then be preached on the houſe toppe.</hi> As the Lord ſpake vnto <hi>Dauid,</hi> by the mouth of <hi>Nathan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.12.</note> ſo ſhall it be then done to euery one; <hi>thou didſt it ſecretly, but I will doe this thing before all Iſrael, and before the Sunne.</hi> The Sunne, yee know, doth ſhine into eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cranie and hole, neither can there any thing be hid from the heat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: when the Sunne of righteouſnes doth appeare, can there any thing bee hid from the heat of his furie, or the bright beames of his piercing ſight? Then <hi>Apices Iuris,</hi> your quirkes, and nice diſtinctions of the law will not helpe; neither Iudges nor witneſſes can be deluded; corruption, ſmooth perſwaſion, and fauour ſhall be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether baniſhed; thy whole life, and all the actions of thy life ſhall be there read, and manifeſted vnto the whole world; there ſhall not be a confuſed capitulation of thy crimes bound vp
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5944:14"/>in a groſſe ſumme and deliuered in the totall; which if it might be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the wicked, they would not much regard their ſtanding in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but that the Iudge of all the world, may make appeare vnto the whole world, his <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>righteous iudgement;</hi> the <hi>ſinnes</hi> of the wicked ſhal particularly be manifeſted in that day, as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Baſil</hi> well noteth.
<note place="margin">Lib. de vera virgin.</note> As the linia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a picture, are euery one by themſelues knowen; ſo ſhall euery mans actions there bee manifeſted; This <hi>our bleſſed Sauiour</hi> doth intimate vnto vs, when he ſayth, <hi>there is nothing hid which ſhall not be manifeſted, what is ſpoken in the eare, ſhall be preached on the houſe toppe.</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> doth likewiſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme this ſpeaking in theſe words of the Pſalme, <hi>When thou ſawest a thiefe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.18, 21.</note> 
               <hi>thourunneſt after him, thou art partaker with the adulterers; theſe things haſt thou done, and I held my tongue, and thou thoughtest wickedly, that I was like vnto thy ſelfe, but I will reproone thee and ſet them in order before thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The bleſſed Apoſtle S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5944:15"/>in the Apocalyps,
<note place="margin">Reutl. 20.12.</note> concerning our appearing in that day, ſaith, <hi>That the bookes were opened,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Liber vitae &amp; liber conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae.</note> 
               <hi>and the dead were iudged of thoſe things which were written in the bookes, according to their workes.</hi> There ſhall bee two bookes opened in that day; the booke of life, and the booke of euery mans conſcience, the booke of the conſcience is a true copy of the booke of life: here a man may finde how it is written there. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of a mans conſcience, if it be true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerued, is a certaine and infallible euidence of the record in heauen. If thou bee written in the booke of life, thou ſhalt haue ſome aſſurance hereof in thine owne conſcience. Thus Saint <hi>Paul</hi> found it written, in the booke of his owne conſcience; that becauſe he had fought a good fight, and kept the faith,
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.8.</note> he doubted not, but that a crown of righteouſneſſe was laide vp for him in heauen, which the Lord, the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Iudge would giue him in that day. It is betweene God and man, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Creditor</hi> and <hi>Debitor,</hi> both keepes bookes, and when they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5944:15"/>to reckon, they both bring forth their bookes, and examine the one by th'other. When the Phariſees brought the woman taken in adultery, before our Sauiour Chriſt, hee ſaid nothing, <hi>but ſtouped downe,</hi> and with his finger,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.6.</note> wrote on the ground. While wee liue in ſenſualitie, and take our pleaſure, our al-ſeeing God obſerueth it, he hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his peace, and ſeemeth to vs not to heare or ſee, which cauſeth vs to bee ſecure in our actions, but in the meane time hee writeth vp all our faults, and <hi>ſealeth them vp in a bagge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 14.17.</note> as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and one day will lay them open before vs. Whatſoeuer is written with the <hi>iuyce of a Limmon</hi> at the firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth not, but hold it a little to the fire, and then yee may read it plainely. The Lord doth now write all our ſins, as if it were with <hi>Limons iuyce,</hi> that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt they appeare not vnto vs to bee ſinnes. <hi>Who is priuie to his ſecret faults,</hi> or who <hi>knoweth how often he doth offend?</hi> But in that great day of Chriſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, when all our workes ſhall be tryed with fire, then ſhall they appeare
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5944:16"/>what they are: there need no witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to accuſe any man in that day, <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia palam fient,</hi> all ſhall bee laid open; the booke of euery mans conſcience will manifeſt his faults; <hi>conſcientia mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le teſtes,</hi> a mans own conſcience wil be vnto him as a thouſand witneſſes; <hi>quid prodeſt non habere conſcium, habenti con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiam,</hi> thou needeſt no witneſſe to come againſt thee, thine owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience wil condemne thee: and if our owne hearts condemne vs, God is greater then our hearts, and knoweth all things:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern. Med. c.</hi> 13</note> 
               <hi>Peccata mea celare non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, quoniam quocunque vado conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia mea mecum,</hi> ſaith holy <hi>Bernard;</hi> I cannot hide my ſinnes, for whitherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer I goe, my conſcience is with mee, it carieth with it whatſoeuer I haue laid vp in it, be it good or euill: it kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth for mee while I liue, and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore vnto me when I am dead; if I do amiſſe it is preſent,
<note place="margin">Accuſat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtientia, teſtis memoria, &amp;c.</note> and priuy to it. Thus haue I in mine owne boſome, my Iudges, my witneſſes, my accuſers and my tormentors. The conſcience is the accuſer, the memory witneſſe,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5944:16"/>reaſon the Iudge, delight torment, and feare the priſon; thus our conſciences ſhall make manifeſt our deedes, when our booke is examined with the booke of life: ſo that to conclude, in the preſence of the Iudge, in open view of all the world, we ſhall bee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted. For we muſt appeare.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> But here wee muſt obſerue, that,
<note place="margin">Obſeruation. <hi>Manifeſtatio Hypocritatum.</hi>
               </note> in that day men and women ſhall be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted two maner of waies. 1. Some ſhall be reuealed to be that which they did not ſeeme to bee in the world.
<note place="margin">A prophanis ſcriptoribus ſic vocati, vt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert Caluinus in ſua, Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</note> 2. Others ſhall appeare to bee that which they were in the world. And for the further manifeſtation of theſe two, conſider all men and women as they are <hi>Actors</hi> vpon the <hi>Theator</hi> of this world; and you know that <hi>Actors</hi> vpon a Stage, are of two ſorts; either they be <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> ſo they were named in former times, becauſe they did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the perſons of thoſe, that they were not: one playeth the part of a King and is no King, another acteth the Merchant and is no Merchant, &amp;c. Others againe, act the perſons of ſuch
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5944:17"/>as they are, one playeth the drunkard, another the whoremaſter, a third the foole, the fourth the Deuill, and the fifth the part of a rogue, <hi>nihil valent omnes,</hi> and ſo they are. In like maner, In that day many that haue ſeemed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men to be honeſt, ciuill, charitable, and religious, when the vizards ſhall be pulled from their faces,
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.16.</note> ſhall appeare to haue beene plaine hypocrits; <hi>they haue had a ſhew of godlineſſe,</hi> but in their actions, they haue denyed the power of it; as the cruell King, the wicked Iudge, the vniuſt ſteward, the oppreſſing officer, the griping land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord, the complementall courtier, the racking rake-ſhame of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, that ploddeth among the commons to lay impoſition vpon the ſubiect, for to benefit the King as hee pretendeth, but his intent is like that of the vniuſt ſtewards in the Goſpel, for to get vnto himſelfe ſome meanes of liuing: all ſuch ſhall bee manifeſted in that day. The cunning pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that hath a tricke to cozen his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor in Tythes, with two leaſes, or elſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5944:17"/>by way of fine ſeeke to defeate the Lord of his due, in that day cannot deceiue the great <hi>Paſtour of our ſoules;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.25.</note> for there he ſhall appeare to bee a <hi>ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious robber,</hi> and all ſuch as haue <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus linum ſubtilitatis, extra lanam ſimplicitatis,</hi> a linſey-wolſey garment, the outſide lambes wooll, &amp; the inſide foxes furre, ſhall be manifeſted in that day. Againe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſome will appeare true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their coulours as they are,
<note place="margin">Vera manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatio impiorum</note> as <hi>Baſill</hi> well noteth; The whoremaſter in his affectation, the drunkard in his abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the blaſphemous ſwearer in his execration; the proud man, the liar, robber, and the deboaſcht man in that day ſhall appeare in their perfect pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, and bee throughly manifeſted to the Iudge, and to the whole world, <hi>and bound hand and foote, and caſt into vtter darkeneſſe,</hi> from whence they ſhal neuer bee deliuered; for if they ſhould breake the chaines through their ſtrength, yet they ſhall ſee no light whereby to eſcape, for the place is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> vtter darkeneſſe; and thus much of the wicked mans ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5944:18"/>in that day. <hi>For all muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <note place="margin">Manifeſtatio piorum.</note> the godly that are now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiled, ſlandered, hated, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the wicked, ſhall then appeare how falſely they are accuſed, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily vſed in this preſent world, when their cauſes ſhall bee knowne, <hi>the word of the Lord ſhall trye them:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 105.19.</note> they ſhall be exalted in the ſight of the world and ſhine <hi>like ſtarres,</hi> in regard of their puritie and ſinceritie, before the Iudgement ſeat; <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> that was accuſed falſely, by his Miſtris con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and caſt into priſon wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, was not more glad, when hee was exalted by <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in the ſight of the people, then theſe; when they ſhall ſtand before the Iudge with dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and be honoured in the ſight of the whole world. In regard whereof, that day will be pleaſant and glorious vnto that litle flocke of Gods children; <hi>for here we ſee in a glaſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.12.</note> (ſayth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>but there wee ſhall know as wee are knowen;</hi> here wee are perſecuted there ſhall wee be glorified;
<note place="margin">Luk. 12.32.</note> 
               <hi>Feare not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5944:18"/>litle flocke, it is my fathers pleaſure to giue you a kingdome:</hi> Now wee are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the ſcumme of the earth, then ſhall wee be preferred aboue the lords of the earth.
<note place="margin">Matth. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed are the poore in spirit, for theirs is the kingdome of God;</hi> this is our ioy and comfort, that in that day wee ſhall be manifeſted.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Let this doctrine be a terrour to the wicked,
<note place="margin">Io. 3.19.</note> that now loue darkeneſſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then light, becauſe their deeds are euill: when euery thing commeth foorth into the light, it ſhall be iudged by the light.
<note place="margin">Matth. 12.36.</note> Our bleſſed Sauiour tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs. <hi>that of euery idle word that men ſhall ſpeake, they ſhall giue account thereof at the day of Iudgement.</hi> Let no filthie communication, no idle and vaine oath proceed out of your mouthes, you that are prophane, obſcoene and wicked: Nay our very thoughts ſhall be called in queſtion: Why thinke yee euill in your hearts you hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites?</p>
            <p>And let it bee as a ſpurre vnto the godly, to ſtirre them vp to an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and godly conuerſation, that they
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5944:19"/>may walke in a good conſcience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and in the ſight of men, knowing, that in that day <hi>they muſt be manifeſted.</hi> I will conclude this point, with a ſtorie out of <hi>Damaſcen;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Damaſc. Hiſt. inter Barlaam and Ioſaphat. Cap.</hi> 13.</note> A man had three friends, two of them hee loued dearely and regarded much, but on the third hee looked with a ſquint eye, litle reſpecting him: it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened on a time, that this man was ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted; and vpon the ſodaine, being taken <hi>tarde,</hi> and not knowing what to doe, he made his way to his beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued friend, to entreat him, by all the bonds of loue, to goe before the iudge with him: which hee denying, ſaide that hee durſt not looke the Iudge in the face, but all the fauour that hee could doe, was, to giue him ſo much as to beare his charges in his iourney: Vnto the ſecond he made haſte, who anſwered him ſo likewiſe: At laſt hee came to the third, whom hee leaſt of all reſpected, and told him how it was with him; vnto whom hee anſwered with great comfort, that although (ſayth he) thou haſt litle regarded me,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5944:19"/>yet I will goe to the Iudge with thee, and cleare thee immediatly. So it is with euery man in this world that hath theſe three friends: The firſt which a man moſt regardeth, is his money and wealth which hee dearly loueth: the ſecond his friends, kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke and acquaintance, whom hee next reſpecteth: but the laſt is the leaſt that hee looketh vpon, and it is his owne <hi>conſcience:</hi> this man is arreſted with the Sergeant of death to ſtand before the Iudge of heauen and earth; at which time, his money nor his wealth cannot helpe him: to buy a wynding-ſheet, a coffin, to giue a pennie dole or the like, is the furtheſt they can goe: His friends likewiſe can doe no more but accompanie him to the buriall, there remaineth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, in that day, but a <hi>cleare conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> to quite him before the Iudge; let vs, therefore, reſpect our conſcience more then all things beſides in the earth, for it muſt onely helpe vs in that day, when wee ſhall bee manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted; For wee muſt all appeare.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:5944:20"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In the third place wee haue the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie or ineuitabilitie of this appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance;
<note place="margin">The neceſſitie of our appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> things that are driuen by force, are moſt violent; therefore to ſet forth the terrour of this Iudgement, our bleſſed Apoſtle addeth an <hi>oportet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The reaſons why there muſt be ſuch a day.</note> 
               <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitate coacta,</hi> to ſhew that there bee no meanes to eſcape, no waies to auoide it; and that for many reaſons. <hi>Opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet,</hi> it muſt be ſo.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1 <hi>Propter decratum Dei;</hi> becauſe it hath beene ſo decreed of God from the beginning: and whatſoeuer the Lord hath appointed from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning muſt ſtand.
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.2. Heb. 6.18.</note> God is not like man; <hi>to lye, or dye,</hi> nor like the <hi>Sonne</hi> of man, <hi>that he ſhould repent: he hath appointed a day wherein he will iudge the world in righteouſneſſe, by that man whom he hath appointed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 17.31. Math. 11.22.</note> ſayth the Apoſtle in one of his ſermons: <hi>it ſhall be better for Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus and Sidon in the day of Iudgement then for this citie,</hi> ſayth our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour: the Prophets before the Law did propheſie of it, our Sauiour affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it in the Goſpel; and all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles beare witneſſe of the ſame in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5944:20"/>their ſeuerall writings: <hi>Oportet</hi> ergo,
<note place="margin">Luke. 21.33.</note> 
               <hi>Heauen and earth ſhall paſſe, but one word or title that is ſpoken out of the mouth of God ſhall not fall to the ground vneffected:</hi> For it muſt be.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2 <hi>Propter Iustitiam Dei;</hi> becauſe it ſtandeth with Gods Iuſtice. All the wicked are not puniſhed in this life; for, although <hi>Caine, Pharaoh, Saul,</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 21.23.</note> receiued ſome temporall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment in this life; yet <hi>Iob</hi> tels vs, that many wicked men <hi>ſpend their daies in iollitie, and ſuddenly go downe to their graues,</hi> without any puniſhment at all.
<note place="margin">1. King. 21.29.</note> Wicked <hi>Ahab</hi> did not ſee the euill threatned vpon his houſe in his dayes. Againe, the godly, for the moſt part, receiue no great comfort in this life; <hi>That I haue fought at Epheſus with beaſts after the manner of men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.32.</note> 
               <hi>What adnanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth it me if the dead riſe not at all,</hi> ſaith our bleſſed Apoſtle; therefore it ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with the Iuſtice of God, to ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon a day wherein euery one may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue according to their actions. And it muſt be ſo: <hi>Nam oportet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3 <hi>Propter noſtram corruptionem,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:5944:21"/>becauſe of our corruption: for, <hi>fleſh and blood cannot inherite the kingdome of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.50.</note> 
               <hi>neither can corruption inherite in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption.</hi> There muſt bee a day of purging;
<note place="margin">Apoc. 21.27.</note> for, <hi>no vncleane thing can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the kingdome of heauen;</hi> a day, when the fire muſt be put to the met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, the fanne to the corne, that the droſſe and chaffe being done away, the pure mettall may appeare more glorious, and the corne finer on the floore;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.54.</note> 
               <hi>When mortalitie is ſwallowed vp of immortalitie, and that which was ſowen a naturall bodie, ſhall bee made a ſpirituall bodie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem</hi> 44.</note> then ſhall bee brought to paſſe this faying that is written by him that is able to bring all things topaſſe, <hi>Nam oportet,</hi> for it muſt be. </p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4 <hi>Propter noſtram manifeſtationem,</hi> as it is in my text, becauſe of our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation, to ſhew publikly what we are, and what wee haue beene. A man cannot iudge of a thing vntill hee ſee the end of it, <hi>Exitus acta probat,</hi> no man can iudge of a mans life to bee good or euill as long as he liueth, but
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5944:21"/>by the outward appearance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dici<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> beatus ante obitum nemo, ſuprema<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> iudicia debet. Nabal</hi> dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed like a lambe,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.37.38.</note> had no reluctati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no bands in death; and yet the Scripture pointeth him out for a wicked man. Many of Gods children are ſtricken ſodainly with death, ſo was <hi>old father Eli,</hi> who is accounted to be a godly old man in Scripture: Therefore there muſt be a day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Iudge of all the world will ſhew his righteous iudgments to the world; and giue vnto euery one according to that which they haue done in their body, whether it be good or bad, as it followeth in my text, <hi>For wee muſt all appeare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> This, <hi>must,</hi> ſeemeth to be ſo ſtrict a charge,
<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that (I doubt) will not ſound well in a young mans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are, that liueth in pleaſure, and runneth vp and downe after his delight. An heathen Author doth tell vs that this age (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning youth) will endure no admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, much leſſe this, to tell them that they muſt come to iudgment.
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 14.29.</note> 
               <hi>Ionathan</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:5944:22"/>will needs taſte of the hony, although his father hath forbidden it. We reade of <hi>purple ſinnes and crimſon ſinnes</hi> in Scripture, colours that will not light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fade, for they are both dyed in the wooll and in the cloth. Young men wil be ſure not to forſake their wicked waies when they are old, they will be ſo perfect in them while they are young: but let them reioyce neuer ſo much in their youth,
<note place="margin">Eccles. 11.9.</note> although their hearts cheare them with delight, and they walke in the wayes of their heart, and after the luſt of their eyes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may ſwimme in pleaſure by the Deuils perſwaſions; yet let me tell them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem</hi> 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>That for all theſe things God will bring them to Iudgement. Remember thy Creator now in the daies of thy youth, whileſt the euill daies come not, wherein thou ſhalt ſay thou hast no pleaſure in them: for in that day of Chriſts appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance thou ſhall bee brought forth into Indgement. Oportet enim:</hi> It muſt be ſo.</p>
            <p>Againe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>I beleeue,</hi> it will not ſound well in a couetous rich mans eare,
<note place="margin">In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that taketh pleaſure in his riches, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5944:22"/>his minde vpon the world. No doubt, that ſpeech which the Spirit of God ſpake vnto the rich man in the Goſpell; <hi>Hac nocte,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.20.</note> that he ſhould ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainely depart from his riches which he ſo much loued, was terrible vnto him: and this will be as grieuous vnto any wretched worldling, to tell him he muſt come to Iudgement: I thinke this ſound neuer doth enter into his eares, there is <hi>maius ſenſibile,</hi> another thing giues a greater ſound:
<note place="margin">Pro. 30.14.</note> it is the voyce of the Horſeleach, <hi>giue, giue.</hi> It is no maruell that they cry vnto the <hi>Mountaines in that day to fall on them;</hi> for it is readieſt in their hearts and mouthes; they thinke of nothing, ſpeake of nothing, nor dreame of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe all their life long but moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of gold and ſiluer. Concerning his temporall eſtate, and the prouiſion belonging thereunto, hee is wiſe and politicke enough, (witneſſe that rich man in the Goſpell) he can haue his bils and bonds well noted in a booke, and make all his accounts readie for his worldly eſtate. But concerning his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5944:23"/>ſpirituall eſtate, he is altogether igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; neither doth he expect any day of account, and to learne he will not frame himſelfe, nor yet will be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted: <hi>Let God doe to himſo, and more al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo:</hi> for he will not <hi>giue to the poore, feed the hungry, nor clothe the naked:</hi> he will rather haue good ſecuritie for ten in the hundred for the preſent, then haue an hundred for ten in expectation. But let al ſuch earthly <hi>Muckwormes</hi> know, that they muſt bee manifeſted before the ſeat of Iudgement; <hi>Oportet enim,</hi> For we muſt appeare, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <note place="margin">Inſacrilegos.</note> it will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound in the eare of a <hi>ſacrilegious Church-Robber,</hi> that taketh away <hi>ſuccum Pastori,</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance from the Miniſter. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it followeth, that <hi>lac ſubducitur agnis,</hi> there the people muſt needs pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for want of milke; ſuch as would haue the <hi>Kings daughter all glorious within,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 45.13.</note> but would not haue her <hi>outward garments of wrought gold, nor of needle worke,</hi> ſuch as would allow but <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas wages</hi> to the Cleargie, for ſo it is that the <hi>fat Buls of Baſon would beate
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5944:23"/>out of the manger the oxen that tread out the corne:</hi> but let all ſuch know, that they ſhall be manifeſted in Iudgment.</p>
            <p>And finally, let all the wicked in the land know this, that <hi>oportet illos omnes,</hi> they muſt all appeare, to receiue accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their deeds. I will conclude this with an <hi>Ode</hi> which I found, an auncient ſinging concerning this laſt Iudgement. <hi>Quis orabit pro delicto? Quis ſpondebit pro conuicto? Quis in iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio tam ſtricto, fiet in praeſidium? Quid ſum miſer tum dicturus? quem patronum rogaturus; dum vix iuſtus eſt ſecurus, cum veniet in iudicium?</hi> Which I Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh thus according to the letter; <hi>Who ſhall pray for his offence? Who ſhal anſwer after ſentence? or who ſhall bring any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in this ſtrict arraignement? What then ſhall I catiue ſay? What aduocate can I pray, ſeeing the iuſt can hardly ſtay, when he commeth vnto Iudgement?</hi> We muſt all appeare, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I haue by this time, ruſhed through this great Aſſembly, and compaſſed this <hi>Iudgement ſeat,</hi> where I haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of the perſons cited, the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5944:24"/>manner of their enditement, and the ſpeciall motiues vrging. Now follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, to ſtand before the ſeat, and then to take view of it, and the Iudge that ſitteth vpon it: and firſt I will ſpeake of the <hi>Tribunall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> A <hi>Tribunall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Tribunall.</note> among the Romans, was a place where the Iudge ſate, ſo called, <hi>Quia tres tribuni ibi ſedebant ad iudicandum populum:</hi> Becauſe three Tribunes ſate there to iudge the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Or, <hi>quia dabant iura tribubus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they gaue Iudgement to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The Greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dior,</hi> to goe vp on ſteppes; which both do well ſet forth the eminency, maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and glory of the place. <hi>When the Sonne of man commeth in his Maieſtie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25.31.</note> 
               <hi>and all his holy Angels with him, then ſhall he ſit vpon the Throne of his glorie.</hi> At his firſt comming hee came in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie and pouertie:
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>In forma ſerui,</hi> ſaith our bleſſed Apoſtle, In forme of a Seruant: <hi>Non ſerui ſolum vt ſubeſſet, ſed vt mali ſerui vt vapularet;</hi> Not onely as a Seruant to vndergoe ſubiection, but as an euill ſeruant to ſuffer corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5944:24"/>But at his ſecond comming, he wil ſhew himſelfe as a King, to be ſerued and miniſtred vnto, in glory and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie: <hi>I ſaw a great white Throne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 20.11.</note> 
               <hi>and one that ſate on it, from whoſe face ſled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way both earth and heauen,</hi> ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle Saint <hi>Iohn.</hi> Some haue gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to deſcribe this <hi>Throne</hi> or <hi>Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> more curiouſly then profitably. They doe deſcribe it what it is, and where it will be placed, or ſeated; which opinions I will briefly relate vnto you. We finde (ſay they) three attributes giuen to it inſcripture. Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quomodo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur.</hi> Math. 25.31. Apoc. 20.11.</note> it is deſcribed by our bleſſed Sauiour, to be a <hi>Throne of glory, The Sonne of man ſhall ſit vpon the Throne of his glory:</hi> and it is ſo called becauſe of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall and glorious comming in that day. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the Euangeliſt <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſaith thus, <hi>I ſaw a white Throne,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the innocencie of him that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on it. And thirdly,
<note place="margin">Dan. 7.9.</note> the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith;
<note place="margin">His Throne is ſaid to be of fire for fiue reaſons.</note> 
               <hi>That this Throne was like a fiery flame, and his wheeles like burning fire:</hi> and that is ſpoken in reſpect of fiue reaſons, which are taken from the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5944:25"/>fire. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, in regard of the <hi>cleareneſſe,</hi> for in his preſence there ſhall bee no darkneſſe, but all cleare light; euery thing ſhall be manifeſted. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, becauſe the light ſhall bee ſuch, that <hi>euery eye ſhall ſee him,</hi> and hee ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto all. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, to ſhew the flame of his furie, and the hot burning coales which hee will ſcatter vpon the wicked. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, to ſhew, as fire paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſwiftly through, and cannot bee hindered in the force of it: ſo in that day his wrath will burne like fire, and none ſhall hinder his proceedings in Iuſtice. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> And laſtly, in the execution of Iuſtice he will bee like fire to purge the droſſe from the pure Mettall; the one like chaffe or droſſe, ſhall burne blacke with vnquenchable fire and Brimſtone; the other like good Gold, ſhall not be hurt with the flame.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Will ye know whereof this <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal</hi> ſhal be.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Materia ex qua.</hi> Apoc. 14 4.</note> Nothing in heauen, <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubim</hi> nor <hi>Seraphin,</hi> Sunne nor Star, nor in earth Gold nor precious ſtone, but, as I read, a cloud ſhal be his <hi>Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. I looked</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5944:25"/>a white cloud, and vpon the cloud one ſitting like to the Son of man, hauing on his head a golden Crowne, and in his hand a ſharpe Sickle.</hi> Which is ſpoken of <hi>Christ,</hi> and this ſeemeth to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the ſpeech of the Angel vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe that looked vpon Chriſt, when he was taken vp. <hi>Why ſtand yee gazing into heauen? this Ieſus which is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp from you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall ſo come as yee haue ſeene him goe into heauen.</hi> And it is ſaid in the verſe going before, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 
               <hi>That a cloud tooke him vp out of their ſight.</hi> Likewiſe at his <hi>transfiguration,</hi> which is a type of his ſecond comming, It is ſaid, <hi>That a cloud did compaſſe him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 17.5.</note> Concerning the forme of this <hi>Tribunall,</hi> we haue no warrant, and therefore will leaue all ſuppoſed coniectures vnto the curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
            <p>There be many opinions concerning the <hi>place</hi> where this <hi>Tribunall</hi> ſhould be ſeated, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <note place="margin">Locus in qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and where the Lord will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to iudge his people. It ſhall not be in <hi>Heauen,</hi> for thither cannot the wicked come to behold him: nor yet in <hi>Hell,</hi> for thither ſhall not the godly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5944:26"/>come to Iudgement: on the earth, I cannot ſee how it ſhould bee, ſeeing there is no place ſo large of earth to containe ſo many <hi>Myriades</hi> of people as ſhall appeare in that day:
<note place="margin">Ioel. 3.2.</note> that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of ſome, grounded on the words of <hi>Ioel,</hi> hath no ſure foundation; that it ſhall bee in the <hi>valley of Iehoſhaphat,</hi> that is onely an alluſion vnto <hi>Iehoſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phats victory,</hi> that as he got the victorie in that place ouer his enemies, ſo ſhall the Lord get the victorie, and victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly triumph ouer his enemies in that day: but (I thinke) his <hi>Tribunall</hi> ſhall be in the ayre, <hi>where euery eye may ſee him,</hi> according to that of the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 4.27.</note> 
               <hi>We which remaine ſhall bee caught vp alſo with them in the cloudes to meet the Lord in the ayre, and ſo ſhall wee be euer with the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there can bee no <hi>Materiall</hi> nor <hi>locall ſeat</hi> preſcribed vnto <hi>Chriſt</hi> truly at his comming, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> for there is no ſuch thing reuealed vnto vs: our Apoſtles meaning here is onely to ſet forth the Maieſtie of his comming. Moſt of the auncient and the Moderne Writers,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:5944:26"/>doe ſignifie by Tribunall, <hi>Iudiciariam poteſtatem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 28.18.</note> a iudiciarie power which is giuen vnto him of the Father (<hi>All po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is giuen vnto me in heauen &amp; in earth,</hi> ſaith our bleſſed Sauiour) <hi>poteſtatem regendi, poteſtatem iudicandi,</hi> power both to gouerne and to iudge: ſo that by <hi>Tribunall</hi> is ſet forth his <hi>dignitie,</hi> his <hi>authoritie,</hi> his <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> and alſo the <hi>certaintie</hi> of his comming: and that we muſt all appeare.</p>
            <p>I will now paſſe from the Throne, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
               <note place="margin">Iudex.</note> to him that ſitteth on the Throne, and heere in my Text he is ſaid to be <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by whom we ſhall be iudged: and here I will paſſeouer many obiections, and draw briefly towards a concluſion.
<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.22.</note> The Father is not our Iudge; for the Father iudgeth no man: nor yet the holy Ghoſt, for the holy Ghoſt would rebuke the world of ſinne, of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and of Iudgement. <hi>All Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is committed to the Sonne.</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Sermon ſaith, <hi>That the Lord hath commaunded vs to preach vnto the people, and to testifie that it is he that is ordained of God, to be the Iudge of quicke and dead.</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:5944:27"/>This Iudge muſt bee Chriſt for ſundry reaſons.
<note place="margin">Cur Chriſtus Iudex.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe of his <hi>affinitie</hi> with vs, in that he hath taken our nature vpon him, for in the ſame fleſh and forme that he was adiudged by <hi>Pontius Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> in the ſame manner ſhall he come to iudge <hi>Pontius Pilate:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>We haue not an high Prieſt</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes) that cannot bee touched with the feeling of our infirmities, but was in all things tempted in like ſort, yet without ſinne; therefore let vs goe to the Throne of grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Becauſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> by Chriſt ſhall all the dead bodies be raiſed in that day,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.22.</note> 
               <hi>As by Adam all dye, ſo by Chriſt all are made aliue,</hi> ſaith the bleſſed Apoſtle: <hi>I am the reſurrection and life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 11.25.</note> ſaith our bleſſed Sauiour.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Becauſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> both good and bad muſt appeare, as you haue heard, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt the Sonne of God, God and Man, muſt bee the Iudge: for the wicked cannot ſee the face of God, they ſhal be depriued of that comfort, which ſhall onely be afforded vnto the godly.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:5944:27"/>
            <p> That he ſhall come to <hi>Iudgement,</hi> this word, <hi>Christ,</hi> in my Text doth verifie, for he was annointed for this purpoſe to vndergoe this office, and doth daily annoint vs to prepare vs for it: he took our fleſh with him into heauen, as <hi>a pawne of his comming,</hi> and left with vs his Spirit, to make vs fit <hi>for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</hi> Then the certaintie of our reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and Chriſts comming to Iudgement, is firmely teſtified in my Text; <hi>For we muſt all appeare before the Tribunall ſeat of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>
               </label> This doctrine doth yeeld great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnto the children of God,
<note place="margin">Comfort to the godly.</note> both in regard that there ſhall bee ſuch a day: as alſo that Chriſt Ieſus ſhall bee their Iudge in that day. Now their eyes are full of teares, and their hearts full of griefe, becauſe of the many croſſes and afflictions which they ſuffer in the <hi>val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of this miſery.</hi> The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were neuer more gladder of their departure out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> then the children of God of the comming of the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: then they wil lift vp their heads, <hi>For their redemption draweth nigh.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5944:28"/>it wil be comfortable vnto them that Chriſt Ieſus their elder Brother ſhal be their Iudge, becauſe of his equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and humanitie. <hi>Abel</hi> went willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the field with <hi>Caine,</hi> expecting no hard meaſure at his hand, becauſe he was his brother. <hi>Iſaac</hi> went freely to the Mount with <hi>Abraham,</hi> looking for no ſeuerity of him, becauſe he was his father. The children of God, with a chearefull countenance, will come out to Iudgement, becauſe their elder Brother is there.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And as this is a comfort to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note place="margin">A terrour to the wicked.</note> ſo it is a <hi>terrour to the wicked;</hi> that there ſhall bee ſuch a <hi>iudgement,</hi> and that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall bee the <hi>Iudge:</hi> The Scripture maketh mention of ſome that doe not beleeue <hi>the Lords com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to iudgement,</hi> becauſe he doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay his comming; others there bee that put off the <hi>terrour of this day</hi> from them. It is reported, that the <hi>Italians</hi> do vſe to ring their bells and diſcharge their cannons in a thunder-clap; that the noiſe of the one may leſſen the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the other: In like manner, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:5944:28"/>(I thinke) doth hang <hi>tinkling cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals</hi> at the eares of earthly men, and delighteth them ſo with the muſick of the world; that, thereby they may forget the ſound of the laſt trumpe. I doubt that day will bee ſeene of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, before it bee foreſeene of any. It will prooue more terrible vnto them then that day of the promulgating of the <hi>Law</hi> did vnto the Iſraelites;
<note place="margin">Exod. 19.18.</note> for if the <hi>promulgation of the Law</hi> was feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, how much more will the <hi>execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> be more fearfull? if his voice was terrible to thoſe that came to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend him; in ſo much,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 18.6.</note> that they <hi>fell backward to the ground</hi> when they heard it, how ſhall the wicked ſtand before his wrathfull voice in that day?
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.10.</note> If <hi>Adam did hide himſelfe</hi> for feare of the Lords furie after his tranſgreſſion; how much more would the wicked hide themſelues, if they had any place to hide them in, from the voice of the <hi>Lambe that ſitteth on the throne?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 45.3.</note> If <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> brethren were mightily amazed, and ſo daunted that they could not ſpeake, when he told them that hee
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5944:29"/>was their brother <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> becauſe of the euill that they had committed againſt him: how much more will the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked bee aſtonied, when they ſhall ſee their brother Chriſt in ſuch glorie and great Maieſtie, whom they haue pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and perſecuted with their wicked life?
<note place="margin">Apo. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>Euery eye ſhall ſee him, yea euen they that pierced him; and all the Nations of the earth ſhall waile before him. Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent quia mundum dilexerunt, plangent quia vitam in mundo non correxerunt, plangent quia fidem non habuerunt:</hi> the couetous man ſhall waile, becauſe hee loued the world more then God and godlineſſe; the laſciuious man ſhall waile, becauſe, for a little pleaſure hee hath purchaſed euerlaſting paine; the vnbeleeuing wretch ſhall waile, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did not beleeue in Chriſt, nor in the trueth of the Goſpel; the proud man ſhall waile, becauſe hee did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the baſe humilitie of the croſſe of Chriſt; and all the wicked men and women ſhall weepe and waile, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did not weepe nor waile in time, while they liued in the world.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5944:29"/>
               <hi>Remember theſe things now, all yee that forget God, leaſt the Lord come in his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie againſt you, and there be none to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you;</hi> let the feare of iudgement perſwade you from your wicked courſes.</p>
            <p>Thou that <hi>blaſphemest the name of God</hi> with execrable oathes, filling vp euery ſentence with an oath or a curſe; remember <hi>the gnaſhing of teeth</hi> after iudgement. Let the thiefe, robber and couſener thinke on them that ſhall be <hi>bound hand and foot and caſt into vtter darkneſſe</hi> in that day. Let the drunkard looke vpon the glutton ſcorched in the flame, <hi>and cannot haue one droppe to coole his tongue withall.</hi> Thou that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thy pleaſure, conſider the damned crew of the wicked that ſhall bee grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly aflicted in that day. Thou that liueſt idlely on the ſweat of other mens browes, call him to minde that hid his talent in the earth, <hi>was bound hand and foot and caſt into vtter darknes</hi> in that day. Thou that art couetous in griping other mens goods, &amp; grinding the faces of the poore with thine own goods, Conſider the <hi>gnawing worme</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:5944:30"/>that ſhall continually gnaw and grinde thee in <hi>hell torments</hi> in that day. Wee read that he that had not vpon him a <hi>wedding garment</hi> was put out, and hee that did deferre his <hi>maſters comming</hi> was not accepted. In that day ſhall the godly looke vpon him with great ioy and comfort, but the wicked ſhall behold him with great feare and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. In that day ſhall hee ſeparate the ſheepe from the Goats: the ſheepe he will place on his right hand, and take them vp with him into theayre, (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh) that all the world may know them, and honour them as Saints; but the wicked he will place on his left hand, leauing them on the earth which they haue ſo much loued, that all may behold them and deſpiſe them as ſinners. The <hi>Iudge</hi> ſhall ſit aboue them, to their great ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: Beneath them, <hi>Hell</hi> ſhall be open readie to receiue them: Before them the <hi>deuils and damned crew</hi> readie to execute Gods wrath vpon them: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them the <hi>Saints and all their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt friend,</hi> forſaking them: On their left hand <hi>their ſinnes</hi> accuſing them:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:5944:30"/>On their right hand <hi>Iuſtice</hi> threatning them: On all ſides the <hi>whole world</hi> burning and flaming about them. It is no maruell that they ſeeke death; but death flyeth from them, they call vnto the <hi>mountaines and rockes,</hi> and they refuſe to couer them; they ſhall dry vp and conſume away for the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſquietneſſe of their ſoules. To goe forward it is intollerable, to goe backward impoſſible, to goe to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide vnauaileable. Thus at the worlds end, men ſhall be at their wits end; but happie ſhall that ſeruant be, whom the Maſter, when he commeth, ſhall find ready prepared and looking for his comming; ſuch ſhall bee ſung in with that ſweet harueſt ſong, <hi>Come yee bleſſed children of my father, receiue the kingdome prepared for you before the beginning of the world:</hi> To the which kingdome, that he may bring vs, let vs daily pray, for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, that hath dearly bought vs; to whom with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, be all honour, glorie and dominion for euer and euer.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
